

Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

□+17378650618 | ■sooyong109@gmail.com | • sooyong1/

Professional Summary

I am a psychometrician with expertise in applying modern statistical theories and techniques. My research interests are in the development and application of statistical models such as such as structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), and item response theory (IRT). Recently, I have focused on Bayesian estimation to model the relationships among variables.

Education

Korea University

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, Texas 2017-Present

Ph.D.

· Major in Quantitative Methods

Seoul, Republic of Korea

M.A.

2014-2017

· Major in Educational Statistics and Measurement

Research experience_

CGS PhD Career Pathways project

Graduate Research Assistant

2018/9-2019/5

• Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

PRESIDENT'S AWARD FOR GLOBAL LEARNING (PAGL)

2019/1-2019/8

· Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/9-2019/12

 $\bullet \ \ \mathsf{Data} \ \mathsf{analysis} \ \mathsf{for} \ \mathsf{surveys} \ \mathsf{of} \ \mathsf{graduate} \ \mathsf{programs} \ \mathsf{of} \ \mathsf{education} \ \mathsf{at} \ \mathsf{the} \ \mathsf{Univer} \mathsf{isity} \ \mathsf{of} \ \mathsf{Texas} \ \mathsf{at} \ \mathsf{Austin}$

MAAT package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

NORTHWEST EVALUATION ASSOCIATION (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

2021/9-Present

• Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

FLPS project

IES GRANT

Graduate Research Assistant

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2020/6-2020/8

• Internship for developing Shiny app for Embeded Standard Setting

Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2021/6-2020/8

• Internship for developing ESS package for Embeded Standard Setting

Teaching experience

EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling

Teaching Assistant

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER

2020/1-2020/5

PROFESSOR TIFFANY WHITTAKER 2021/1-2021/5

Publications

2021

Cory L. Cobb, Charles R. Martínez, Jr., **Sooyong Lee**, Tae Kyoung Lee, & Elma I. Lorenzo-Blanco (2021). Acculturation trajectories differ by youth age at arrival and time in residency among Latino immigrant families in a US emerging immigrant context. *International Journal of Intercultural Relations*. 81, 79-93. DOI: 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2021.01.005.

2022

- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. *Applied Psychological Measurement*. 46-1, 73-74. DOI:10.1177/01466216211049212.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. 29, 23-35. DOI:10.1080/10705511.2021.1956320.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Parallel Process Latent Growth Modeling with Multivariate Confounders/Suppressors. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. DOI:10.1080/10705511. 2022.2133774.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Kahyun Lee, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Application of Associative Discrete-Time Survival Analysis Using Latent Transition Specification. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. DOI: 10.1080/10705511.2022.2138892.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. 82-4, 678-704. DOI:10.1177/00131644211028995.

2023

- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully-Latent Principal Stratification. *The Annual Meeting of the Psychometric Society.* Conference proceedings, In print.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Comparison between Bayesian or ML in FLPS with Small Sample Sizes. In progress.
- Sooyong Lee, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Multidimensional FLPS. In progress.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2023). Bayesian MIMIC for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. In review.
- Tiffany A. Whittaker, Laura Stapleton & **Sooyong Lee** (2023). A Tutorial for Obtaining Item Response Theory Results from Structural Equation Modeling in Mplus Software with Rating Scales. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. In review.

Presentation

Poster

- Kejin Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Youngri Lee (2018-05-01). *An Alternative Approach to Discrete-Time Survival Analysis for Meaningful Interpretation*. Modern Modeling Methods conference (MMM), Connecticut, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Sehee Hong (2018-07-01). *Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), New York, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2020-04-01). *Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.

- **Sooyong Lee** & Suhwa Han (2020-07-01). *Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Maryland, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2021-04-01). *DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.

Presentation

- Daniel Lewis & **Sooyong Lee** (2021-04-01). *A Comparison of Two ESS Cut Score Estimation Algorithms*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Baltimore, MD, USA.
- Garron Gianopulos, Jay Lee, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04-01). *The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- Jay Lee, M. Christina Schneider, Garron Gia, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04-01). *The Impact of item bank transition rules on student ability estimates and achievement level classifications*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022-07-01). *Fully-Latent Principal Stratiication*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Bologna, Italy.

Program.

GRshiny: Graded response model

Shiny application

2023

https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/GRShiny/

Embeded Standard Setting

Shiny application

2021

• https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS_test/

maat package R package

2022

https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/maat/index.html

FLPS package R package

2022

clavaan package R package

2023

Fellowship & Awards

William Hays Endowed Fellowship

Fellowship

2020-21

Benjamin & Dorothy Fruchter Excellence Award

Award 2021-22